Preliminary Guide to the Louise Hortense Branscomb Papers, 1864-2002 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Louise Hortense Branscomb papers 1864-2002 and undated
Branscomb, Louise Hortense, 1901-
7.95 linear feet Extent: 2040 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
branscomblouise
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Also, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Louise Hortense Branscomb Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1985-2002.
Biographical Note
Physician originally from Alabama.
Collection Overview
Collection (accession numbers 6-17-85, 87-163, 89-122, 90-045) (458 items, 1.4 lin. ft.; dated 1864-1986) contains medical notebooks, correspondence, speeches, photographs, a few pieces of Confederate currency, and one baby book. The medical notebooks contain reports on cases of surgery on women; references to tropical medicine, obstetrics and gynecology, and contagious diseases; medical histories of her patients; and dosages and treatments given. Hospitals where she worked include Woman's Hospital in Philadelphia, Pa.; Franklin Square Hospital in Baltimore, Md., and Hillman Hospital in Birmingham, Ala. One photograph (1909) of banquet at the First Methodist Church, Birmingham includes Rev. Lewis Capers Branscomb, Dr. Branscomb's father; second photo (1934) includes Dr. Branscomb.
Correspondence includes letters written by Branscomb's parents focusing chiefly on their courtship and later family life in Alabama. Speeches written by Branscomb were given at functions of United Methodist Church, Birmingham, and relate to her life as physician and to role of women in the church. Baby book describes episodes in her life from 1901-1907. Also included are papers of Lewis Branscomb, a Methodist minister, composed chiefly of diaries, newsclippings, journals, sermon topics, information about persons at whose funeral he officiated, and lists of baptisms he performed. A container list was not created for these accessions.
The addition (95-067) (25 items, 1.5 lin. ft.; dated 1944-1992) contains Dr. Branscomb's diaries which document in detail her professional and civic activities and her involvement in the Methodist Church, as well as her interactions with friends and relatives. Besides her primary diaries, there are travel diaries recording trips to India, Scandinavia, Africa, Europe, Korea, South America, and China. A container list was not created for this accession.
The addition (98-0513) (6 items, 0.5 lin. ft.; dated 1914-1920) contains six diaries kept while Dr. Branscomb was a teenager, documenting family and school life in Alabama, summer trips to North Carolina, and college life at Women's College (later Huntingdom College) in Montgomery, Alabama. Several of the diaries contain pasted in clippings, photographs, and other ephemera documenting Branscomb's social life and current events. A container list was not created for this accession.
The addition (99-0335) (11 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1992-1993) is comprised of Dr. Branscomb's 1992 diary. Includes photos and clippings. A container list was not created for this accession.
The addition (02-226) (1500 items, 4.2 lin. ft.; dated 1864-2002 and undated, bulk 1984-1999) contains correspondence, clippings, diplomas, photographs, writings, speeches, financial papers, and legal papers of Dr. Branscomb. Materials relate to her family, civic, and church affairs. Also included are a 1902 diary (for part of the year) kept by her father, as well as letters and other papers generated by him, his wife, and their various children. There are also two scrapbooks containing newsclippings, 119 black-and white photographs, and 109 color photographs.
The addition (02-250) (40 items, 0.25 lin. ft.; dated 1985) contains four audio cassettes containing an oral history conducted between September and October of 1985 in Birmingham, Ala., when Martha E. King interviewed Dr. Branscomb on behalf of the Women's Division Oral History Project for the United Methodist Church's General Board of Global Ministries. There is also correspondence, biographical information about Dr. Branscomb, as well as detailed descriptions of and an index for the interview. However, no transcript of the interview is available. Interview topics include family, education, missionary work, women's issues in the church, race relations, and Branscomb's representing the church on her travels to Africa. A container list was not created for this accession.
The addition (07-169) (5 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1980) contains a biography of Dr. Branscomb written by her brother, Rev. Edwin Branscomb in 1980.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Branscomb, Louise Hortense, 1901-; Branscomb, Lewis Capers; Branscomb, Minnie McGehee; King, Martha E.; United Methodist Church (U.S.); Woman's Hospital of Philadelphia -- History; Franklin Square Hospital (Baltimore, Md.)--History; Hillman Hospital (Birmingham, Ala.)--History; First Methodist Church (Birmingham, Ala.); Methodist Episcopal Church -- Alabama; Surgery, Operative; Women in the Methodist Church; Women in Christianity -- United States -- History; Women physicians -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Obstetrics -- Statistics; Gynecology; Diseases; Tropical medicine; Women missionaries; Women in missionary work; Alabama -- Social life and customs; Diaries; Casebooks; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Scrapbooks; Audio cassettes
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2002-0226
  Until June 16, 2029, access is limited to descendants of the donor and to persons receiving prior written permission from those descendants.
  Also contains sensitive information (personal health and financial information). Patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights. Contact Research Services.
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Loose material: correspondence, 1925-1994
      - Personal/friends/family
      - Condolence letters, 1930
      - Cothran family, 1956
    - Family photographs, 1931-2002 and undated
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    [Contains sensitive information (personal health information). Patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights. Contact Research Services.]
    - Loose material: correspondence, genealogical information, 1912, 1930 and undated
      - Condolence letters, 1912
      - Condolence letters, 1930
      - Genealogical information, undated
    - Printed material: Cornerstone and Spire volume about First United Methodist Church, Birmingham, AL
    - Louise Branscomb Personal files, 1950-1999 and undated
      - Travels to Korea and China
      - Methodist Church
      - Personal health information
      - Women's issues
    - Funeral Guest Signature Books, undated
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Louise Branscomb Personal files (some loose material, some printed material), 1920-2002, undated
      - Biographical information and funeral plans
      - Clippings and publications
      - Personal health information
      - Correspondence
      - Personal address book, spelling dictionary
      - Volume about Syngman Rhee, dedicated by Rhee family member
    - Photograph files: family/friends
      - B/W
      - Color
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    [Contains sensitive information (personal health, financial information). Patrons must sign a waiver concerning privacy rights. Contact Research Services.]
    - Louise Branscomb Personal files, 1984-1997, undated
      - Personal medical information
      - Financial information--sale of house
      - Legal information--will
      - Correspondence, family, [1990s]
    - Loose material: correspondence, genealogical information, 1930-1996
      - Diary, 1902 (L.C. Branscomb)
      - Correspondence
      - Draft of Louise Branscomb memoirs, 1993
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Loose material: correspondence, 1886-1997
      - Family/friends
        - Donald Riddle, [1940s]
        - Greek correspondents
        - One Spanish language letter
      - Official (church, donations to organizations)
      - Professional
      - Condolence letters, 1930
    - Funeral flower arrangement cards, 1930
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Coin Purse, undated
    - Methodist buttons/medals, 1970, 1976, undated
    - Address book (metal), undated
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Issue of Alabama Christian Advocate, 1930 Sept.
    - Scrap Book (1) of news clippings, 1864-1898, undated (contains Confederate $100 bill)
    - Scrap Book (2) of news clippings and leaflets, 1901-1926, undated
  - Contents of Oversize Folder 1: (Box Oversize 16)
    - Diplomas and certificates